Guide to the Board of Trustees records, 1821-2003 RG0001
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Committees, 1911-1960; RG0001 Series 5; 4 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5, Box 6, Box 7, Box 8)
  - Committee on Public Relations--meeting minutes, 01/27/1955 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Text on folder "Mr. Farrington's presentation of work being carried on by the Office of University Development; Mr. John Gonella's public relations survey. Being considered for employment at the University; Mr. Ludewig Caminita's philosophy pertaining to public relations; Mr. Farrington to make survey of public relations policies of other universities and prepare a statement for this University."
  - Committee on Public Relations--meeting minutes, 07/18/1947 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Text on folder "Relationship between Alumni Office and Director of Public Relations."
  - Committee on Public Relations--meeting minutes, 07/18/1947 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Text on folder "Question of organization of alumni and public relations department; Report from Lester Smith; Decision to allow department to evolve with little additional help; Coordination of alumni and public relations under Vice President Grant; Two contact officers, Director of Alumni Relations and Director of Public Relations to be appointed."
  - Committee on Educational Planning, Memoranda, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Special Committee to Consider the Future Leadership of the University, 03/04/1959 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Text on folder "Joint Meeting of the Executive Committee and the Special Committee to Consider the Future Leadership of the University. Minutes filed under Executive Committee."
  - Special Committee on Patent Law Foundation, 7 December, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Special Committee on University Planning, correspondence, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Special Committee on Redevelopment, correspondence, 1957 -1958 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Committee on Resolutions, correspondence, 11/09/1927 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Special Committee on Scientific Contracts, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Special Committee on a religious Center, meeting minutes, 05/03/1960 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    Text on folder "The Committee voted to recommend that the Board approve in principle the proposed plan for a Religious Center at the University an that Dr Sizoo and the Acting President be authorized to proceed with the preparation of preliminary plans and securing of cost estimates."
  - Committee representing the University on National Capital Area Hospital Council, correspondence, 1945 -1946 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Special Committee on Site for Medical School, meeting minutes, 05/21/1954 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    Text on folder "Dean Bloedorn's report on his contacts with prospective donor; Decision for President Marvin and Dean Bloedorn to study number of square feet required in new building; Decision in favor of Square 40 for site of new building."
  - Special Committee to Locate House for the President of the University, 10/13/1960 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    Text on folder "No minutes taken. Recommendation by the Committee presented to the Board of Trustees on this date."
  - Special Committee to Survey the Financial Policy of the Hospital, 02/1950 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    Text on folder "With special reference to the renewal of the loan of $350,000 secured on the Medical School and the old Hospital."
  - The Special Committee to Survey the Financial Policy of the Hospital and the Committee on Finance, 02/21/1951 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Report of Special Committee on Hospital Finance, 1952 -1953 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Special Committee on Lisner Auditorium, correspondence, 1946 -1947 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Honor Committee, minutes and transcripts of hearings, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Washington Home for Foundlings, 12/06/1947 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    Text on folder "Re: Proposed affiliation with the George Washington University. Three (3) copies enclosed. Original filed with Minutes of Board Meeting."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/11/1959 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Text on folder "The Committee reviewed the personnel changes recommended by the appropriate officers and deans, and the Acting President, and voted to recommend their favorable consideration by the Board of Trustees. The Committee thought it a good idea to invite a particular Dean from time to time to discuss before the Board specific matters falling under his cognizance which the Board had under consideration. Acting President Colclough said he would take the matter up with Chairman Fleming. Discussion of action taken by Board on February 8, 1934: "It was voted that after the close of the present fiscal year the University would not employ two members of the same family." At present there are 3 cases of married couples contributing their services to the University without compensation. The Committee voted to recommend to the Board that the action taken on February 8, 1934, be interpreted as not barring the employment of two members of the same family both of whom contribute their services to the University without compensation."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 12/05/1958 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Text on folder "The committee reviewed the personnel changes recommended by the appropriate officers and deans, and the President, and voted to recommend their favorable consideration by the Board of Trustees. Approval of President's recommendation to offer Mr. Robert Faris a five-year contract with the understanding that during that period Mr. Faris would have the opportunity to develop himself that he might merit academic status and eventually tenure. Discussion of the continuation of George Wythe, Professorial Lecturer in Economics, during spring term although he would normally retire in February because of age. The committee felt that recommendations for the continuation of part-time members of the staff beyond the normal retirement age should be kept to an absolute minimum. The committee adjourned."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 03/07/1958 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Text on folder "Personnel changes for 1958 and for 1958-59. President Marvin commended Dean Elmer Louis Kayser for his fine service as acting administrative officer for School of Government, pending appointment of a Dean. It was recommended that his compensation for this service be $1250 for each semester served. Approval by the Committee to recommend Section 3, Article VII be changed in the Code and Ordinances Governing the Academic Personnel, making it possible for an officer of administration to be recommended by the President for Emeritus status."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 12/06/1957 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Text on folder "The Committee reviewed personnel changes which have been approved by the President since the last meeting of the Personnel Committee on October 8, 1957, and recommended these changes for presentation to the Board."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 10/08/1957 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Text on folder "Personnel changes for 1957-58. Approval of change in "Ordinances and Rulings Governing the University and College Faculties" re academic status of some administrative officers, namely that of the possibility of promotion in professorial status as recommended by the University administration and approved by the Board"
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/02/1957 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Text on folder "Personnel changes for 1957 and for 1957-58. Approval of the Revised "Code Governing the Academic Personnel." To be presented to the Board on May 9, 1957. Administrative staff and other non-academic personnel retirement policy was approved."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 01/31/1957 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    Text on folder "Personnel changes for 1967-57 approved since the last meeting of the Board in December, 1956. Personnel changes for 1957-58 were approved. Discussion about proposal for certain members of the faculty to be given emeritus status but to continue in residence with a limited amount of teaching and no administrative duties."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 12/11/1956 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    Text on folder "Personnel recommendations since the last meeting of the Board in May, 1956. Report that committees had been appointed to advise the President concerning selection of a Dean for the School of Medicine and a Dean for the Law School. Preliminary information concerning report of the committee to study the Faculty Code. Reaffirmation of the ruling that two members of the same family may not be employed by the University."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/08/1956 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Text on folder "Personnel recommendations for the current year and for 1956-58. Dean Colclough described the background and experience of the new full-time appointees and requests for leave. Resignation of the Dean of the Law School, John T. Fey. Difficulty in securing full-time personnel in science, engineering, and pharmacy."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 03/15/1956 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    Text on folder "Promotions for: Chester Hayden McCall, Jr. to Asst. Prof. of Statistics, LeRoy Sorenson Merrifield to Professor of Law"
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/01/1956 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Text on folder "Personnel items for the current academic year. Personnel items to be included in the 1956-57 budget. President mentioned problems in the Hospital: number and salaries of nurses, interns, residents, and secretaries; union contract; and minimum wage of $1 per hour."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 10/07/1955 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    Text on folder "Request form Mr. Hoebreckx of Milwaukee for Board policy on Communism. Statement sent but further action deferred until later meeting of Committee. Regular personnel changes since May 19, 1955. Death of Professors (Retired) Cheney and Donaldson noted with regret."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/11/1955 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    Text on folder "Promotion of Dr. Gordon S. Letterman approved. Promotion of Dr. William Carey Meloy was not recommended by the administrative officers. Regular Personnel Changes since Mar. 31, 1955. Death of Dr. Radford Brown noted with regret."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 03/25/1955 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    Text on folder "Regular Personnel Changes since Feb. 10, 1955. Promotion of William Carey Meloy and Gordon S. Letterman considered. Referred back to administrative officers. Retirements considered; no recommendation at this time. Faculty honored at Alumni Luncheon for completion of 25 years of service."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/03/1955 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    Text on folder "Regular personnel changes since October 14, 1954. Appointment of Mr. Stanley J. Tracy as Director of project on Population Migrations with Richardson Foundation, Inc. Resignation of Myron L. Koenig as Dean of Junior College. Leave with Salary approved for Mrs. Lilian Smith, Garden Consultant."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, Correspondence, 10/21/1952 --05/23/1955 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 10/06/1954 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    Text on folder "Routine Personnel Changes. Approval for leave of absence for Dr. Kraus, Dr. Mosel, and Dr. Wise."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/13/1954 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    Text on folder "Approval of personnel changes. Professor Bessman not to be reappointed because of political philosophy. Committee concurred in the decision."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/06/1954 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    Text on folder "Approval of personnel changes. Rules pertaining to Administrative and Research Staffs - Recommendation for changes in the rules adopted on April 1, 1954."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/04/1954 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    Text on folder "Approval of personnel changes. Rules pertaining to Administrative and Research Staffs - Recommendation to rescind rulings of Oct. 12, 1950."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 12/09/1953 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    Text on folder "Discussion of code for administrative assistants. Personnel approvals."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 04/30/1953 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    Text on folder "Retirement. Appointments. Promotions. Resignations. Deaths."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 04/01/1953 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    Text on folder "Retirement policy of the University. Personnel Changes for 1953-54."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 10/08/1952 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    Text on folder "Personnel changes approved. Death of Anna Pearl Copper noted. Retirement Compensation resolution substitution studied."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/08/1952 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    Text on folder "Personnel changes approved reconsideration of the recommendation of Dr. Calvin Klopp tenure to the Director of Activities for Men; Women salary increases for 1952-53 budget."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/07/1952 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    Text on folder "Changes in Personnel recommended by the President approved."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 10/08/1951 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    Text on folder "increase for the Custodial and Hospital Staff effective March 1, 1951. President discussed his attitude re communists - Committee agreed University should not employ them. Personnel changes approved."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 10/05/1950 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    Text on folder "Discussion of union contract which University has for Custodial and Hospital Staffs. War Leave policy statement. Social Security Act 1950. Rules and Regulations Applicable to Administrative Assistants and Research Staffs. Review of personnel changes."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/08/1950 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    Text on folder "Review of Personnel Matters for presentation to Board on 2/9/50"
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 10/12/1949 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    Text on folder "Postponement of Sabbatical Leave for Assoc. Prof. Helen B. Lawrence. Discussion of union organization as it affected the hospital."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/05/1948 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 12/10/1946 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    Text on folder "Personnel changes. Reestablishment of Sabbatical Leave. Sabbatical Leave Grant to Professor John Donaldson. Discussion of accelerated program."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/20/1947 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    Text on folder "Presentation of new salary scale for 1947-48 budget. Presentation of appointments, resignations, changes in status and sabbatical leaves. Discussion of Professors Griggs, Spaulding, and Ragatz."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 03/11/1947 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    Text on folder "Appointments, resignations and changes of status recommended to Board. Discussion of retirement policy (Professor Robert f. Griggs). Approval of recommendation to Committee on Finance for salary increases."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/11/1947 (Box 7, Folder 35)
    Text on folder "Appointments, resignations and changes of status recommended to Board. Sabbatical leave granted for Associate Professor Audley Lawrence Smith."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 12/04/1947 (Box 7, Folder 36)
    Text on folder "Review of personnel changes. Annual report by members of the faculty discussed. Resignation of Maurice Brown Greenough, Asst. Prof. of Civil Engr. Emeritus status for John Donaldson discussed."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 09/23/1947 (Box 7, Folder 37)
    Text on folder "Personnel Changes. Retirement of Professors Donaldson and Smith. Sabbatical Leave for Associate Professor Lawrence."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 10/03/1946 (Box 7, Folder 38)
    Text on folder "Recommendation re salary scale for Administrative Assistants. Approval of above scale emphasis made of conditions of employment. Approval of appointments for Summer and Fall Terms, resignations, changes of status and leaves of absence. Report from Hospital Council of National Capital Area to be effection at George Washington University Hospital September 26, 1946. Further study recommended regarding leaves of absence."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/13/1946 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    Text on folder "Discussion of personnel problems re maintenance staff. Approval of changes in administrative staff and faculty."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 10/09/1945 (Box 7, Folder 40)
    Text on folder "Changes in personnel. Establishment of post of associate professor of pharmacology - Paul K. Smith to be appointed. Establishment of post of clinical instructor in pediatrics at $1,800. Establishment of post of supervisor of postgraduate instruction. Criticisms of the Law School. Establishment of the Reading Clinic."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 03/06/1945 (Box 7, Folder 41)
    Text on folder "Faculty and administrative changes. Organization of the University faculty. Retirement plan for faculty and staff."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 12/12/1944 (Box 7, Folder 42)
    Text on folder "Establishment of Washington Counseling Center. Administrative changes. Faculty changes."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/23/1944 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    Text on folder "Resignations, appointments, leaves of absence, changes of status. Suggestion that appointments as submitted to Committee indicate replacement or creation of new position. Establishment of new division--division of counseling and assignment. Changes in personnel suggested in the event of establishment of such a division. Suggestion that the President prepare a chart showing University organization."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 03/07/1944 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    Text on folder "Appointments, resignations leaves, promotions, retirements. The case of Professor Courtland Darke Baker."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/08/1944 (Box 7, Folder 45)
    Text on folder "Leaves of absence, resignations, appointments."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 10/12/1943 (Box 7, Folder 46)
    Text on folder "Changes in personnel. Dr. Harry H. Donnally to me made Professor Emeritus at convocation of 11/17/43. Public relations: Alumni Secretary in charge of public relations. Mrs. Lennice DeBooy named public relations assistant. Approval of action of Executive Committee in appointing Miss Atwell Women's Activities Adviser. Submission of salary scale to War Labor Board for foreman ans [and] assistant foreman. Supervisor of trainees assigned by Veterans Administration."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/25/1943 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    Text on folder "Changes in personnel. The case of Steuart Henderson Britt. Exemption of University from maintenance of 48-hour week. Report of submission of salary schedules to War Stabilization Board."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 03/03/1943 (Box 7, Folder 48)
    Text on folder "Faculty changes. Salary scale for administrative and maintenance assistants. Salary scale for hospital employees. Positions of engineer and janitor for Lisner Auditorium."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 12/08/1942 (Box 7, Folder 49)
    Text on folder "Leaves, appointments, and resignations since meeting of the Board on October, 1942. The case of William J. Reinhart. Policies in regard to war leaves."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/26/1942 (Box 7, Folder 50)
    Text on folder "Action concerning faculty reaching retirement age. Approval of promotions and salary increases. Resignation of Mr. Merry as Business Manager and appointment of Mr. Connolly. Salary of Alva Curtis Wilgus."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/10/1942 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    Text on folder "Division of Extension and appointment of Director Hall. Policy of filling only vital posts vacated during the war. Principles governing promotion referred to President and faculty committee. Principle governing retirement during the war. Amendment to Section 6 of "Rules and Regulations Applicable to the Administrative Assistants."
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 12/09/1941 (Box 7, Folder 52)
    Text on folder "Adjourned meeting"
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 10/08/1941 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    Text on folder "Approval of personnel changes. Function of the Committee. The case of Professor Wilgus. Approval of regulations pertaining to administrative assistants.
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/20/1941 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - Committee on Personnel--correspondence and meeting minutes, 10/10/1940 --12/12/1940 (Box 7, Folder 55)
    Text on folder "Resolutions put before Board 10-10-40 and 12-12-40 Re Establishment of Com. on Personnel"
  - Committee on Public Relations--correspondence and meeting minutes, Correspondence, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Overhead Model photographs of GWU block plan, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Committee on the University Hospital--correspondence and meeting minutes, 04/20/1959 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Text on folder "Report on internships and residencies accepted by the Committee; Discussion of the first seven pages of the proposed revisions of the By-Laws, Rules, and Regulations Governing the Medical Staff of the University Hospital. Some changes were adopted by the Committee. The Committee adjourned."
  - Committee on the University Hospital--correspondence and meeting minutes, 03/03/1959 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    Text on folder "Courtesy Allowance Policy for the Hospital approved; Discussion of By-Laws, Rules and Regulations Governing the Medical Staff of the University Hospital. This item is to be considered at the next meeting of the Committee; Report on Internships and Residencies to be presented at a later meeting; Report on forthcoming Congressional Hearing on medical costs in the District of Columbia be a Senate subcommittee."
  - Committee on the University Hospital--correspondence and meeting minutes, 12/08/1958 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Text on folder "Approval of recommendation for addition of a residency in the Dept. of Surgery in the field of plastic surgery to be used in the Hospital and Cancer Clinic; President Marvin suggested a study be made of the internships and residencies re number of positions and compensation; Report on Courtesy Allowance Policy was represented. It will be considered at a later meeting after review by the Treasurer; Approval of recommendation establishing Intensive Care Unit for critically ill post-operative patients. The meeting adjourned."
  - Committee on the University Hospital--correspondence and meeting minutes, 07/01/1958 (Box 8, Folder 5)